Inventory of the Raymond R. White Collection
Hoover Institution Archives
Raymond R. White Collection
1966-1985
2011C10
Raymond R. White
3 manuscript boxes, 4 oversize boxes and 1 oversize banner (4.0 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
The Raymond R. White collection consists of documents relating to the Stanford antiwar movement and to the wider radical political and countercultural scene in the Palo Alto area in the late 1960s and early 1970s. White was a member of a conservative group, the Stanford branch of the Young Americans for Freedom (YAF), that actively opposed campus radicals during this period. Along with other YAF members, White systematically collected materials published by and pertaining to Stanford radicals and the demonstrations that they organized. He also collected leaflets, pamphlets, and serial issues published by a variety of New Left organizations and counter-cultural groups in the greater Palo Alto area. The White collection includes some posters and a considerable number of fugitive and ephemeral materials not found in other collections pertaining to radical political movements at Stanford and in its vicinity during this period.
Administrative Information
Access
Boxes 1-2 are CLOSED
The remainder of the collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2011.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in Socrates is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Related Materials
New Left collection, Hoover Institution Archives
Stanford Draft Counseling Office collection, Hoover Institution Archives
Biographical Note
1950 Born, New Rochelle, New York
1967-1976 Studies at Stanford University, where he is active in conservative student groups
1973 Awarded doctorate in biology, Stanford University
1982-present Teaches biology at City College of San Francisco
Scope and Content of Collection
The Raymond R. White collection consists of documents relating to the Stanford antiwar movement and to the wider radical political and countercultural scene in the Palo Alto area in the late 1960s and early 1970s. White was a member of a conservative group, the Stanford branch of the Young Americans for Freedom (YAF), that actively opposed campus radicals during this period. Along with other YAF members, White systematically collected materials published by and pertaining to Stanford radicals and the demonstrations that they organized. He also collected leaflets, pamphlets, and serial issues published by a variety of New Left organizations and counter-cultural groups in the greater Palo Alto area. The White collection includes some posters and a considerable number of fugitive and ephemeral materials not found in other collections pertaining to radical political movements in the Peninsula during this period.
While much of the White collection centers on the antiwar movement, it also has materials relating to the case of Stanford University professor and Venceremos leader H. Bruce Franklin, whose teaching career at Stanford ended in 1972, after prolonged proceedings initiated by the Stanford administration. Franklin's dismissal was controversial at the time, as were his political views. In addition to being a tenured English professor, Franklin was the leader of Venceremos, a Maoist organization that openly advocated armed struggle as part of its revolutionary program. The result of a split within the Revolutionary Union (which later became the Revolutionary Communist Party), Venceremos aligned itself with the Black Panther Party and other militant organizations active in the San Francisco Bay Area at the time.
The White collection comprises the largest set of documents in the archives specifically relating to Stanford and its environs during the turbulent era of the Vietnam War and the mass protests that arose in opposition to it. Although its creation and order were determined by the conservative political agenda of White and his collaborators, the collection will provide researchers with a detailed view of the groups that were most active in the radical movement at Stanford and in the Palo Alto area at the time. It will also show that Stanford had its own radical milieu, and although it was much smaller than the Berkeley movement of the same era, it was one that had a significant impact on campus life.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Stanford University.; Radicalism--United States.; Student movements--United States.
Collection Contents
- CLOSED (Box 1-2)
- Printed matter, 1966-1985 (Box 3-7)
  Contains clippings, leaflets and pamphlets, serial issues, miscellaneous bulletins and issuances, and posters, arranged alphabetically by physical form. Materials largely relate to the Stanford antiwar movement, as well as to radical organizations and the counter-culture in the Palo Alto area, 1966-1973. Includes some right-wing publications
  - Clippings, 1969-1985 (Folder 3: 1-5)
  - Leaflets and pamphlets, 1969-1973 (Folder 3: 6-10)
  - Serial issues, 1966-1973 (Folder 3)
    - Tocsin, 1966 (Folder 3: 11)
    - Campus Report, 1970-1973 (Folder 3: 12)
    - The Real News, 1971 (Folder 3: 13)
    - The Stanford Daily, 1970-1973 (Folder 4-6)
  - Miscellaneous bulletins and issuances, 1971-1972 (Folder 7: 1)
  - Posters, 1970-1971 (Folder 7)
    - People Need People, 1970 (Folder 7: 2)
    - Street Wall Journal, no. 1, 1970 (Folder 7: 3)
    - The Farm News, 1971 (Folder 7: 4)
    - Laos Invaded! Laos Invaded!, 1971 (Folder 7: 5)
    - War Criminal Comin' to Town, 1971 (Folder 7: 6)
- Oversize banner, 1970 (Box 8: 1)
  Protest banner relating to Liberation College and the imprisonment of Black Panther Party leader Bobby Seale